Guide to the Records of The Bolivia Project RISM RG 8
New York University Archives
Records of the Bolivia Project
Bulk, 1964-1967
1964-1997
RISM RG 8
New York University Archives
140.0 linear feet
The RISM Bolivia Project was initiated in 1964 at the request of the U.S. Peace Corps. Headed by Dr. Vera D. Rubin, founder and director of RISM, and Dr. Lambros Comitas, assistant director of RISM, anthropological and epidemiological teams studied six ecologically distinct communities in order to identify major health problems and to assess the implications of rural social organization to facilitate the work of development agencies. The Bolivia Project generated thousands of documents, including correspondence, accounting records, indexed field notes, laboratory processing records, surveys and questionnaires, epidemiological data, maps, photographs, microfiche and microfilm. The collection also includes appended items from an exhibition, Retrospect and Prospect: Preservation and Use of Archival Materials in the Digital Age, which celebrated the Bolivia Project. Appended items include exhibit brochures, information panels, oversized computer generated charts, and video tapes.
Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM).
Arrangement
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Accounting Records
III. Indexes
IV. Epidemiological Research
V. Ethnographic Research Records
VI. Surveys and Questionnaires
VII. Microfiche
VIII. Microfilm
IX. Project Reports
X. Unpublished Manuscripts
XI. Community and Regional Maps
XII. Photographs
XIII. Miscellaneous Papers
Appendix: Audiovisual Materials
Appendix: Exhibition Material
Appendix: Computer Cards
Appendix: Publication Materials
Appendix: Photocopied Materials
Appendix: Reports from RISM to the Peace Corps, Partial Reports Related to the RISM Bolivia Project, 1964-1967
Separated Material
No materials have been removed from the collection.
Scope and Contents
The Bolivia Project (1964-1967) consists of 200 linear feet of materials, including correspondence, accounting records, biographical index cards, indexed field notes, epidemiological and ethnographic studies and reports, laboratory processing records and results, blood typing cards, health questionnaires, computer generated charts, questionnaires and surveys that focus on household sanitation data and investigation of infant feeding habits, community censuses, maps, oversized charts, microfiche, microfilm, articles, unpublished manuscripts and accounting records, photographs, and videotapes. Material from a 1997 exhibit, Retrospect and Prospect: Preservation and Use of Archival Materials in the Digital Age, has also been appended to the collection.
Historical/Biographical Note
In 1964, at the request of the U.S. Peace Corps, the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) initiated a three-year epidemiological and ethnograpic research project in Bolivia.
Headed by Dr. Vera Rubin, RISM's founder and director, and Lambros Comitas, assistant director, the Project employed more than eighty social and medical scientists and assistants. Organized as teams, researchers lived in six rural communities. Each community represented a major organizational type, ranging from minimally stratified and nonpolitical to complex stratification and politically revolutionized. Four of the communities were situated in the rural towns of Villa Abecia, Coroico, Reyes and Sorata, and two were in the Indian pueblos of Compi and San Miguel (see map).
The region had been impacted by major social reform in 1952 when the Nationalist Revolutionary Movement (MNR) took power. New, politically mobilized campesinos from the rural Aymara and Quechua populations redistributed part of the country's national resources. The MNR made a number of efforts to integrate the society, which was stratified yet culturally heterogeneous and regionally oriented. Some of these most important efforts involved land reform, nationalization of the tin mines, establishment of institutional supports for the working population, and the dramatic expansion of rural education.
The project had two interrelated research objectives. The epidemiological team attempted to define the major problems of health and disease in rural Bolivian communities, taking into account the different ecological regions of the country. The ethnographic team delineated the major social features of each community by conducting a comparative study of social relations and social processes. Numerous volumes of ethnographic and sociological data were generated and subsequently used in comparative studies that included an extensive social survey of heads of households. This epidemiological and ethnographic research became fundamental to the planning of future community development programs and provided insight into the dynamics of community problems and community change.
However, the complexity of the research and analysis, as well as the interest in the application of scientific knowledge, resulted in more than a third of total project funding being provided by RISM. The methodological and theoretical development of the Project, as well as the research findings, were detailed in a report developed during the period of study. Quarterly reports, describing the work and the course of research, were filed with the Peace Corps. The epidemiological teams systematically sampled each community, and the results were entered into a database. The material was subsequently organized, analyzed, and used to prepare the final epidemiological report and summary of findings on health levels and health behavior. The final publication, Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia, was published in November 1967 and translated into Spanish ( Estudios Epidemiologicos en Bolivia) by the epidemiological research team.
The ethnographic report was published in 1969 as Changing Rural Bolivia and in 1971 by Oxford University Press as Changing Rural Society. In addition, a number of articles, reports, theses and doctoral dissertations resulted from the project research.
Sources:
Preface, Changing Rural Bolivia: Final Anthropological Report for the Peace Corps. New York: Research Institute for the Study of Man, 1969.
Retrospect and Prospect: Preservation and Use of Archival Materials in the Digital Age. Exhibition of the RISM Bolivia Project 1964 - 1967.
"Theory and Methodology of the RISM Bolivia Project," unpublished Mss.
Access Restrictions
The Collection contains human subject data and unpublished manuscripts. Some material may be restricted.
Provenance
The materials associated with the Bolivia Project were created by teams of epidemiological and ethnographic researchers between 1964 - 1967 and transferred to the New York University Archives in 2006.
Comitas, Lambros; McEwen, William J.; Novick, Victor; Peace Corps (U.S.).; Rockefeller Foundation.; Rubin, Vera D.; Torre, Mottram; Articles.; Census records.; Charts (graphic documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Coroico |z Bolivia.; Correspondence.; Epidemiology.; Ethnology |z Bolivia.; Field notes.; Filmstrips.; Ggrey literature.; Laboratory notes.; Manuscripts (document genre).; Maps.; Microfiche.; Microfilms.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Publications.; Quarterly reports.; Questionnaires.; Reyes.; Résumés (personnel records).; San Miguel (inhabited place).; Scripts (documents).; Sorata (inhabited place).; Villa Abecia (Bolivia)
- Series I. Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of 5.5 linear feet of both incoming and outgoing correspondence relating to various phases of the project, arranged alphabetically by the correspondents' last names or subject matter. Also included in this series are final reports, telegrams, clippings, budget papers, notes, memorandum, film strips, articles, and curriculum vitae that are referenced in the correspondence.
  - Administrative: Notes and Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative: Notes and Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnes, Katherine, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beltran, Aguirre, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bernhard, Bambi, Jul 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Berkeley Office and Personnel, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bibliography, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bolivia Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bolivia Office and Personnel, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Budgets, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book Information and Orders, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Budgets, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Buechler, Harris, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - C (General Correspondence), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Champeau, Catherine (Cathy), 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "C.R.B." Contracts and Royalty Statements, 1969, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Changing Rural Bolivia, Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Changing Rural Bolivia, Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings and Articles, Bolivia, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Clippings and Articles, Miscellaneous, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clinica Americana, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Code Books, Bolivia Survey, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Colmen, Joseph (Dr.), 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Comitas, Lambros, undated-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Conferences, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Coroico Team, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Danielson, David, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Data system, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Data system (epidemiology), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Educational References, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Erikson, Edwin, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Epidemiology Study Codes and Lists of Communities and Subcommunities, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Epidemiology Study: Correspondence (related to final report), 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Epidemiological Study: materials related to printing of final report, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Epidemiology Study: Supplies (correspondence), 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Estremadoiro, Winston, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ethnobotany, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Estudias Epidemiologicos en Bolivia," Final Report to Peace Corps, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Field work, general information, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Film Production: Filmstrips + Scripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fisher, Phyllis, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Forms: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Forms and Outlines: Epidemiology Study, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Forms and Outlines: Ethnographic Study, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "G" (General Correspondence), 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "H" (General Correspondence), 1966-1967, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Heath, Dr. Dwight B., 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Heath, Dr. Dwight B., undated-1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Heath, Dwight to William McEwen, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Holcomb, Beverly, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "I" (General Correspondence), 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Insurance, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "K" (General Correspondence), 1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Kentucky, University of, Medical College (Dr. Hugh Fullmer), 1965-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Introduction, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "M" (General Correspondence), 1965; 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Microfilm Project, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miller, Solomon, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Minesterio de Salud Publica, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Muratoria, Blanca, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1961-1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "N" (Correspondence), 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - National Science Foundation Grant Application, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Notes on plants, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Novick, Victor, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Omran, Dr. Abdel R., 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Omran, Dr. Abdel R., 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Omran, Dr. Abdel R. (Epidemiology Study, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "P" (General Correspondence), 1966; 1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Peace Corps: General Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Peace Corps: Public Health Group Terminal Report (Carl A. Moore), 1964 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Peace Corps: Public Health Units, 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Peace Corps: Research Proposal, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Peace Corps: Seminar, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Proposed Bolivia Volunteer Development Corps, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Public Health Service, 1967; 1969 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Quarterly Reports, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Quarterly Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Quarterly Reports (Budget), 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "R" (General Correspondence), 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Reconnaissance, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Reference Publications: "Bolivia's Experiments in Development Without Aid" (Richard W. Patch), 1964 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Reference Publications: "Canton Chullpas, A Socioeconomic Study in the Cochamba Valley of Bolivia" (Olen E. Leonard for the U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1948 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Reference Publications: "Drinking Patterns of the Bolivian Camba" (Dwight B. Heath, Brown University), 1962 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Reference Publications: "El Tifus Exantematico Boliviano o El Tifus Altaplanico" (Instituto Nacional de Bacteriologica), 1935 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Reference Publications: "Santa Cruz: A Socioeconomic Study of an Area in Bolivia" (U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1948 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Releases, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Ressel, Franz, 1964-1970 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Robalina, Elot, 1964-1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Rubin, Dr. Vera (Working Notes), 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "S" (General Correspondence), 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - San Miguel, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Schedules, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "T" (General Correspondence), 1964; 1966-1967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Transportation, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Travel Arrangements and Information, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "U-Z" (General Correspondence), 1966 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Series II. Accounting Records
  Scope and Contents note
  These materials (Boxes 12-15) remain at the Reed Foundation. Please contact the Foundation for access to this series.
- Series III. Indexes
  This series consists of index cards that serve as a quick reference to the original field notes. The cards have been organized into four subseries.
  - Subseries A. Biographical Index Cards
    This subseries contains approximately 5,300 biographical index cards compiled during the processing of ethnographic research materials. These cards do not include names, Community Househould Numbers, or Member of the Household Numbers. The index cards, organized by community, include an alphabetical arrangement of inteviewees, the initials of individual field workers, and page numbers from the original field notes.
    - Compi Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 16)
    - Coroico Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 17)
    - Reyes Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 18)
    - San Miguel Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 19)
    - Sorata Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 20)
    - Villa Abecia Biographical Index Cards A - M, undated (Box 21)
    - Villa Abecia Biographical Index Cards N - Z, undated (Box 22)
  - Subseries B. CSO Indexed Field Notes Cards
    This subseries contains approximately 86,000 Community Study Outline (CSO) indexed field notecards. The cards are organized by community. The CSO index number is noted next to a bracket on the left side of each card, as are the initials of the field worker and the page of the original field notes.
    - Coroico (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Carton 23-67)
    - Reyes (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Carton 68-101)
    - San Miguel (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Carton 102-110)
    - Sorata (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Carton 111-152)
    - Villa Abecia (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Carton 153-178)
- Series IV. Epidemiological Research Records
  The materials in this series relate to the epidemiological study conducted between 1964 - 1967. They have been organized into 11 subseries that document the various research activies.
  Please note that Subseries G-K, which are organized by community, may contain overlapping, combined data.
  - Subseries A. Blood Examination Laboratory Processing Records
    This subseries consists of blood examination laboratory processing records. The material in this series was organized in manuscript form by Dr. Franz Ressel, head of epidemiological laboratory procedures in Bolivia. The test results were indexed by Member of the Household Number.
    - Notebook I, undated (Box 179, Notebook 1)
    - Notebook II, undated (Box 179, Notebook 2)
    - Notebook III, undated (Box 179, Notebook 3)
  - Subseries B. Blood Samples: Blood Typing Cards
    Subseries B consists of 2,192 blood typing cards placed in archival polypropylene binders. The cards in this series, housed to minimize movement and moisture retention, were used for blood typing and indexed by the Member of the Household Number.
    - Compi 1-1 to 64-1, undated (Box 180)
    - Compi 64-2 to 98-5, undated (Box 181)
    - Compi 99-1 to 160-1, undated (Box 182)
    - Coroico 1-1 to 66-1, undated (Box 183)
    - Coroico 66-2 to 133-2, undated (Box 184)
    - Coroico 134-1 to 197-2, undated (Box 185)
    - Coroico 197-3 to 253-1, undated (Box 186)
    - Coroico 253-2 to 270-12, undated (Box 187)
    - Reyes 1-1 to 40-2, undated (Box 188)
    - Reyes 41-1 to 83-1, undated (Box 189)
    - Reyes 83-3 to 127-3, undated (Box 190)
    - Reyes 127-4 to 174-1, undated (Box 191)
    - Reyes 175-1 to 211-1, undated (Box 192)
    - San Miguel 1-1 to 80-1, undated (Box 193)
    - San Miguel 81-1 to 177-2, undated (Box 194)
    - Sorata 2-1 to 62-2, undated (Box 195)
    - Sorata 63-1 to 116-4, undated (Box 196)
    - Sorata 116-5 to 170-1, undated (Box 197)
    - Sorata 170-2 to 177-2, undated (Box 198)
  - Subseries C. Health Questionnaire / Cedula de Salud
    This subseries consists of 1,791 Health Questionnaires (cedulas de salud), organized by community. The Questionnaires were used as a preliminary census that documented the size of households and health conditions of family members. The Questionnaires contain the Community Household Number, written above the page numbers, and the name of the head of household, which may also appear in the existing Biographical Index Cards.
    - Cedula de Salud: Compi, undated (Box 199, Folder 1)
    - Cedula de Salud: Coroico, undated (Box 199, Folder 2)
    - Cedula de Salud: Coroico, undated (Box 199, Folder 3)
    - Cedula de Salud: Coroico, undated (Box 199, Folder 4)
    - Cedula de Salud: Coroico, undated (Box 199, Folder 5)
    - Cedula de Salud: Reyes, undated (Box 199, Folder 6)
    - Cedula de Salud: Sorata, undated (Box 199, Folder 7)
    - Cedula de Salud: Sorata (Box 199, Folder 8)
    - Cedula de Salud: Cruz Loma (Box 199, Folder 9)
    - Cedula de Salud: Mururata (Box 199, Folder 10)
    - Cedula de Salud: Bolivar Cruzani (Box 199, Folder 11)
  - Subseries D. Computer Generated Charts: Census and Distributions
    This subseries consists of statistical charts based on the processed census information of the communities being studied.
    - Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia Printed edition; offset master copy, undated (Box 200-202)
  - Subseries E. Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia [Final Report]
    This subseries consists of materials related to the final report published in 1967 as Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia in English and Spanish.
    - Community Study Outline Material, undated (Box 203, Folder 1)
    - Tables, undated (Box 203, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous chapters, undated (Box 203, Folder 3)
    - RISM. Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia: Final Epidemiological Report for the Peace Corps. New York: RISM, 1967. (2 copies), undated (Box 203, Folder 3)
    - Omran, Abdel R., William J. McEwen, and Mahfouz Zaki. Estudios Epidemiologicos en Bolivia. New York: RISM, 1967. (2 copies) (Box 203, Folder 4)
    - Foreign Areas Study Division, Special Operations Research Office, The American University. U.S. Army Area Handbook for Bolivia. Washington, D.C.: Department of the Army, 1963. (Box 203, Folder 5)
    - McEwen, William J. Changing Rural Bolivia. N.p.: RISM, 1969. (Box 203, Folder 6)
    - Bolivia Nutrition Survey: A Report by the Interdepartmental Committee on Nutrition for National Defense. N.p.: n.p., 1964. (Box 203, Folder 7)
    - McEwen, William J. Changing Rural Society. New York: Oxford UP, 1975. (Box 203, Folder 8)
    - Benitez-Rojo, Antonio. The Scholar and the Collector. New York: Interamericas Society of Arts and Letters, 2000. (Box 203, Folder 9)
    - Rubin, Jane Gregory, and Ariana Donalds, eds. Bread Made from Yuca. New York: Interamericas, 2003. (Box 203, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous box of unidentified negatives and slides, undated (Box 203, Folder 12)
    - Offset copies of both reports, undated (Box 204, Folder 1)
    - Spanish originals: "Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia", undated (Box 204, Folder 2)
    - Original copies of report (2 sets), undated (Box 204, Folder 3)
  - Subseries F. Epidemiological Study Charts
    This subseries consists of charts which were generated during the processing of epidemiological data. Organized by age and gender, the charts were included in the final report.
    **NB: I have been unable to locate this subseries.
    - Ascaris Lumbrocoides Charts Negative/Positive Results (61 pages organized in a binder), undated (Box 1)
    - Double Coding Charts (1151), undated (Box 2)
    - Blood Typing Charts (194), undated (Box 3)
    - Compi (36), undated (Box COMPI)
    - Coroico (57), undated (Box COROICO)
    - Reyes (56), undated (Box REYES)
    - Sorata (45), undated (Box SORATA)
  - Subseries G. Household Administrative Cards
    This subseries consists of 703 cards in compound form that includes Household Sanitation information (Subseries H described below). The form includes the Community Household Number, which indexes the epidemiological study documents, and the name of the head of household, which may be included in the Biographical Index.
    - Compi (1 - 160), undated (Box 205)
    - Reyes (1 - 211), undated (Box 206)
    - San Miguel (1 - 177), undated (Box 207)
    - Villa Abecia (1 - 155), undated (Box 208)
  - Subseries H. Household Sanitation
    This subseries describes the sanitation conditions of the various communities, including water supply, latrines, refuse and cleanliness, animals, and housing conditions. Subseries H records have been filed with those of Subseries G, Household Administrative Cards, and are organized by community.
  - Subseries I. Investigation of Infant Feeding Habits (100)
    This subseries consists of 100 forms comprising a survey of infant feeding habits in Sorata. The forms include the name of the individual being studied and may also appear in the Biographical Index.
    - Sorata (100), undated (Box 209)
  - Subseries J. Laboratory Results/ Pruebas de Laboratorio
    This subseries consists of 5,534 records representating the data collected from 1,186 households in the six study communities, and the schoolchildren of Compi, Coroico, Reyes, LaPaz and Penas. The data is indexed by the Member of the Household Number.
    - Compi (1 - 160), undated (Box 205)
    - Coroico (1 - 270), undated (Box 210)
    - Reyes (1 - 211), undated (Box 206)
    - San Miguel (1 - 177), undated (Box 207)
    - Sorata (100), undated (Box 209)
    - Villa Abecia (1 - 155), undated (Box 208)
    - La Paz Centro de Salud Publica, undated (Box 211, Folder 1)